A Guide to the Travis C. McDonald Papers, 1982-2023
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Travis C. McDonald Papers, 1982-2023
The Library of Virginia
53913
1.4 cubic feet (4 boxes)
Travis C. McDonald
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Travis C. McDonald.
Biographical Information
Travis C. McDonald was the Director of Architectural Restoration at Thomas Jefferson's Poplar Forest in Bedford County, Virginia.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1982-2023, of Travis C. McDonald, Director of Architectural Restoration at Thomas Jefferson's Poplar Forest, located in Bedford County, Virginia. Records consist of materials written by McDonald about Poplar Forest and other aspects of historic preservation and historic sites. Also contains articles, reports, and other documents written by other authors and collected by McDonald regarding historic preservation and historic preservation sites.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged
Series I: Travis McDonald and Poplar Forest, 1991-2023
Series II: Historic preservation and historic preservation sites, 1982-2009
Contents List
- Series I: Travis McDonald and Poplar Forest, 1991-2023 1991-2023, 1 box (Box 1)
  Papers, 1991-2023, of Travis C. McDonald, Director of Architectural Restoration at Thomas Jefferson's Poplar Forest, which is located in Bedford County, Virginia. Records consist of materials published by the Corporation for Jefferson's Poplar Forest, including material written by McDonald; articles written about Poplar Forest by McDonald and published in other sources; and articles written about Poplar Forest by other authors. Also contains articles written by McDonald regarding other aspects of historic preservation and other historic preservation sites.
  - Thomas Jefferson's Poplar Forest: A Private Place, 2002, reprinted 2010 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Notes on the State of Poplar Forest, volumes I and II, 1991, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Notes on the State of Poplar Forest, Spring-Fall, 2020; Spring-Fall, 2022; Spring 2023 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Thomas Jefferson's Poplar Forest flyer (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Travis McDonald, Restoration Highlights and Summary, February 2014 (Folder 5, Box 1)
  - Travis McDonald, Enslaved Workers: Docent Training, 20 September 2016 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Travis McDonald, Poplar Forest Restoration Highlights Chronology, 2023 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Travis McDonald, Significant Aspects of the Design and Restoration of Thomas Jefferson's Poplar Forest, no date (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Travis McDonald, The Brickwork at Poplar Forest: Mr Jefferson Builds His Dream House in APT Bulletin: The Journal of Preservation Technology, volume XXVII, no. 1-2, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Travis McDonald, Poplar Forest: A Most Palladian Villa in Arris:Journal of the Southeast Chapter of the Society of Architectural Historians, volume 28, 2017 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Travis McDonald, Restoring Poplar Forest: Jefferson's Retirement Masterpiece in Magazine of the Decorative Arts Trust, Winter 2002-2003 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Travis McDonald, Constructing Optimism: Thomas Jefferson's Poplar Forest in Perspectives in Vernacular Architecture, volume VIII, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Travis McDonald, Rat Housing in Middle Virginia: The Diffusion of Everyday Life in Perspectives in Vernacular Architecture, volume X, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Travis McDonald, Poplar Forest: Jefferson and Palladio in Spiritual Agreement in Palladiana: Journal of Center for Palladian Studies in America, Fall 2018 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Travis McDonald, Poplar Forest: A Masterpiece Rediscovered in Virginia Cavalcade, Winter 1993 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Travis McDonald, Thomas Jefferson's Poplar Forest: Privacy Restored in Virginia Cavalcade, Winter 2002 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Travis McDonald, The Private Villa Retreat of Thomas Jefferson in White House History, number 18, Spring 2006 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Travis McDonald, Restoration, Re-Restoration and Real History: Trends and Issues in Historic House Museums in Historic Preservation Forum, volume 7, number 6, November-December 1993 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Travis McDonald, Jefferson Builder in Jefferson and Palladio: Constructing a New World, 2015 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Travis McDonald, Jefferson Improves on Palladio in Palladiana: Journal of Center for Palladian Studies in America, Spring 2023 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Travis McDonald, Understanding Old Buildings: The Process of Architectural Investigation in Preservation Briefs 35, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Travis McDonald, Tom the Builder in University of Virginia, Spring 2018 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Travis McDonald, The East and West Wings of the White House: History in Architecture and Building in White House History, number 29, Spring 2011 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Wayne Fields, Jefferson's Second Home in American Heritage, April 1993 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Sandy Hevener, A House: Poplar Forest in Blue Ridge Country, November-December 2005 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Will Holloway, Jefferson Comes Alive in Clem Labine's Period Homes, November 2005 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Jane Brown Gillette, Mr. Jefferson's Retreat in Historic Preservation, July-August 1992 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Dale Mackenzie Brown, Jefferson's Other Home in House Beautiful, December 1997 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Vernon Mays, A Villa Through Time: Thomas Jefferson's Poplar Forest in Inform no. 2, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Janet Martin, Poplar Forest: In Search of the Private Thomas Jefferson in University of Virginia Alumni News, October 1991 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - J. Michael Welton, Jefferson's Retreat Restored in Virginia Living, April 2023 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Kathryn Hensley, Jefferson's Poplar Forest: A Phoenix Rises from the Ashes in Wood Design and Building, number 10, Winter 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Thomas Jefferson Buildings, Virginia in World Heritage in the United States of America: The U.S. Tentative List, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Series II: Historic preservation and historic preservation sites 1982-2009, 3 boxes (Box 2-4)
  Papers, 1982-2009, collected by Travis C. McDonald consisting of articles, appendices, brochures, emails, newsletters, pamphlets, photographs, reports, theses, slides and other documents documenting historic preservation and historic preservation sites in Virginia.
  - Subseries 1: Historic buildings 1985-2009, 2 boxes (Box 2-3)
    - Battersea papers (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Christopher V. Novelli, Battersea Appendices, volume I, October 2005 (Box 2)
    - Christopher V. Novelli, Battersea Appendices, volume II, October 2005 (Box 2)
    - Clifton Ellis, The Mansion House at Berry Hill Plantation: Architecture and the Changing Nature of Slavery in Antebellum Virginia in Perspectives in Vernacular Architecture, volume XIII, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Castle Hill papers (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Mark R. Wenger, Edward Chappell, and Willie Graham, Eppington: An Architectural History, 15 May 1995 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Mesick-Cohen-Wilson-Baker, Architects, Conditions Survey and Recommendations for the Jefferson Addition at the Farmington Country Club, September 2000, Located in Oversize Box 71 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - A Preliminary Outline of the History of the Governor's Mansion, 15 July 1987 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Vernon Mays, A Heritage Regained at the Executive Mansion, in Inform: Architecture and Design in the Mid-Atlantic, number 1, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Edward A. Chappell, Reconsidered Splendor: The Palace Addition of 1751. A Report to the Program Planning and Review Committee, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation, September 1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Kenmore papers (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Maymont papers (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Calder Loth, Menokin: Virginia's Most Unusual Preservation Adventure, in Northern Neck of Virginia Historical Magazine, 16 November 2006 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Thomas Jefferson's Poplar Forest Restoration Field School, Historic Structures Investigation Report: Montezuma, Norwood, Virginia, 2009 (Box 3)
    - Monumental Church papers (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Joseph Manca, George Washington's Eye: Architecture and Landscape at Mount Vernon, book manuscript, ca. 2012 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Mount Vernon papers (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Carl R. Lounsbury, An Elegant and Commodious Building: William Buckland and the Design of the Prince William Courthouse, in Journal of the Society of Architectural Historians, volume 46, number 3, September 1987 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Redlands papers (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Soldier's Joy and Cherry Hill papers (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Michael J. Pulice, The Log Outbuilding at Solitude: An Architectural and Archaeological Investigation of Virginia Tech's Second Oldest Building, Master's thesis, Virginia Tech, May 2000 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Spring Dale papers (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - An Architectural Study of the Buildings at Sully (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Robert P. Hilldrup, The Mansion in Upper Brandon, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - White House of the Confederacy papers (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Subseries 2: Conferences, seminars, articles, and papers 1982-2004, 1 box (Box 4)
    - Vernacular Architecture Forum: 1988 Annual Meeting Staunton, Virginia, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - The Early Architecture of Tidewater Virginia: Twenty-third Annual Vernacular Architecture Forum Conference-Williamsburg, Virginia, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Brochure for Domestic Architecture in Colonial Virginia, Stratford Hall Plantation Architectural History Seminar, 1-4 November 2001 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - S. Allen Chambers, Of the Best Quality: Buckingham Slate in Virginia Cavalcade, Spring 1989 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - S. Allen Chambers, William Lawrence Bottomley in West Virginia in Arris, volume 10, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Heather A. Foster, Wallpaper in Richmond, Virginia, 1785-1908 Master's thesis, Virginia Commonwealth University, May 2000 (Box 4)
    - Willie Graham, Preindustrial Framing in the Chesapeake in Perspectives in Vernacular Architecture, volume 9, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Gardiner Hallock, Pise Construction in Early Nineteenth-Century Virginia in Perspectives in Vernacular Architecture, volume 11, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Donald W. Linebaugh, All the Annoyances adn Inconveniences of the Country: Environmental Factors in the Deveolopmen of Outbuildings in the Colonial Chesapeake in Winterthur Portfolio, volume 29, number 1, Spring 1994 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - William M. S. Rasmussen, Designers, Builders, and Architectural Traditions in Colonial Virginia in Virginia Magazine of History and Biography, April 1982 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Camille Wells, Dower Play/Power Play: Menokin and the Ordeal of Elite House Building in Colonial Virginia in Perspectives in Vernacular Architecture, volume 9, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Camille Wells, The Eighteenth-Century Landscape of Virginia's Northern Neck in Northern Neck of Virginia Historical Magazine, volume XXXVII, December 1987 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Camille Wells, The Planter's Prospect: Houses, Outbuildings, and Rural Landscapes in Eighteenth-Century Virginia in Winterthur Portfolio, volume 28, number 1, Spring 1993 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - The Iron Worker, volume XXVI, number 2, Spring 1962 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - APVA Preservation Virginia brochure, Discover Virginia: A Guide to Virginia's Historic Properties, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Jamestown papers, photographs (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Williamsburg papers (folder 1 of 2) (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Williamsburg papers (folder 2 of 2) (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Orders of Robert Mills (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Architectural history reading list: American Regions and Regionalism, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 19)